Let’s say you really need
to find reliable information
about the best diet for
high blood pressure,
or heart disease,
or diabetes.
Where do you go?
Do you go to a website
sponsored by Big Pharma
that wants to sell you
pills to fix your problem?
Or, do you want
to treat the cause?
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast
with the latest peer-
reviewed research
on the best ways to eat
healthy and live longer.
Today we turn a laser-like focus to
that round tuber we call the potato.
Are they good for us?
Bad for us?
Here’s our first story.
The trouble for white
potatoes began in 2006,
when the Harvard Nurses’ Health
Study, which had followed
the diets and diseases of tens
of thousands of women for 20 years,
found that greater potato
intake was associated with
a greater likelihood of
getting type 2 diabetes.
Okay, but wait. Of the hundred
or so pounds of potatoes
Americans eat every year,
most are in the deep-fried form
of potato chips or French fries.
What happened when they looked
specifically at mashed or baked potatoes?
They found the same link with diabetes.
Okay, but what might
potato eaters eat more of?
I’ll give you a hint by rephrasing that as:
what might meat-and-potatoes
people eat more of?
Indeed, people who ate
more potatoes ate more meat,
and we know that animal
protein on its own
is associated with
increased diabetes risk.
But the researchers tried
to statistically adjust
for that and still found
increased risk with potatoes.
Well, what do people put
on baked and mashed potatoes?
Butter and sour cream. Again,
the researchers tried to adjust
for other dietary factors
like these as well as effectively
looking at the ratio
between plant and animal fats,
and whether potato
eaters drank more soda,
or maybe skimped on other
vegetables, and still
there seemed to be this
potato diabetes association.
Okay, but that was just one study.
By 2015, Harvard researchers had
also looked into other cohorts,
including the all-male Health
Professionals Follow-up Study
to complement the all-
female Nurse’s studies,
and they continued to find a
small increased diabetes risk
associated with baked,
boiled, or mashed potatoes,
though French fries do indeed
appear nearly five times worse.
The authors concluded that
potatoes are considered to be
a healthy vegetable
in dietary guidelines;
however, the current ﬁndings cast
serious doubts on that classiﬁcation.
Walt Willet, the chair of Harvard’s
nutrition department at the time,
went a step further, suggesting potatoes
should be siloed up there with candy.
A meta-analysis of potato consumption
and risk of type 2 diabetes
published in 2018 combined all
six of the prospective studies
that has been done to date, and they
found about a 20 percent increase
in diabetes risk associated with
each serving of potatoes a day,
concluding long-term high
consumption of potato may be
strongly associated with
increased risk of diabetes.
But, again, the great majority of
this potato consumption was fried,
and we know there are all
sorts of nasty things like
advanced glycation end
products in deep fried foods.
The researchers weren’t able to assess
French fries versus non-fried potatoes.
Even just three servings of
fries a week is associated
with nearly 20 percent greater
risk of type 2 diabetes,
whereas there was only a
tiny associated risk with
potatoes in general, and that
included the fries mixed in.
The world’s largest manufacturer
of frozen French fries
took issue with this conclusion,
laying claim to one in three
fries eaten on planet Earth
to the tune of billions of
dollars, they have the money
to fund reviews like this one
to cast doubt on the science.
But they do have an actual point.
Observational studies can
never prove cause-and-effect,
and maybe potato consumption,
even baked potato consumption,
may just be a marker for an
unhealthy diet in general.
As much as researchers try to
adjust for these other factors,
as the journal of the Potato Association
of America is quick to remind us,
it’s not possible to completely
separate the effects
of potatoes and French
fries from the effects
of the overall crappy
Standard American Diet.
If only there was a country
where potato consumption
was associated with a healthy diet.
If potato consumption was still
associated with diabetes there,
then that would be concerning.
But here we go...a seventh study,
but this time out of Iran,
where not only is most of their potato
consumption from boiled potatoes,
but those who eat potatoes had
the healthiest diets and ate
the most whole plant foods—fruits,
vegetables, whole grains, and beans.
And though the researchers
tried to tease out those other
dietary factors, those eating
the most boiled potatoes had
only half the odds of
developing diabetes.
This supports the notion
that it may be hard
to completely separate
out just the potatoes.
The bottom line, this systematic
review concluded, is that
we really don’t have convincing
evidence to date that the intake
of potatoes in general is
linked to type 2 diabetes,
but we should still
probably hold the fries.
In our next story we ask:
do potato eaters live longer or shorter
lives than non-potato eaters?
Potato intake and the
incidence of hypertension.
Harvard researchers followed
the diets and diseases
of more than 100,00 men and
women for decades and found that
those who ate potatoes on most
days—even just baked, boiled,
or mashed, not just French
fries and potato chips—
appeared to be at higher risk of
developing high blood pressure.
Okay, but what do people
put on potatoes?
Salt, not to mention butter; so,
maybe the potatoes are just
innocent bystanders. Maybe...
but the researchers made attempts
to tease out the effects
of salt and saturated fat,
and there still seemed
to be a link between
potato consumption
and high blood pressure.
Maybe potato eaters are just
meat-and-potatoes people.
After all, these same Harvard
researchers have found that
meat, including poultry alone
appeared to be associated with
an increased risk of hypertension,
and the same with even a
moderate amount of canned tuna.
So, in the potato study, they were
careful to try to factor out
any effects from the consumption
of all types of animal flesh.
Yet they still found an increased
potato risk and got concerned
that the association of potato
intake with hypertension
could be a critical
public health problem.
We had assumed
potatoes might actually
decrease high blood pressure
given their high
potassium content,
but they found evidence of
the opposite effect.
Two similar studies performed
in Mediterranean Europe
did not find any association
between potato consumption
and high blood pressure, though.
Perhaps this is because they
don’t smother their potatoes
in butter and sour cream
in that neck of the woods
and instead eat potatoes
with other vegetables.
Now, the Harvard folks tried
to control for the bad salty
and fatty dietary components
associated with eating potatoes
in the West, just like these
researchers tried to factor out
all the extra vegetables, but
you can’t control for everything.
A primary reason we care
about blood pressure is
because we care
about the consequences.
In two studies done in Sweden,
where they primarily eat
their potatoes boiled, no
evidence was found that
potato consumption was
associated with the risk of
major cardiovascular disease,
and no relationship was found
between potato consumption
and risk of premature death
found in Southern Italy either.
In the U.S., however,
potato consumption was
associated with
increased mortality:
a whopping 65 percent increased
risk of dying from heart disease,
a 26 percent increased
in fatal stroke risk,
a 50 percent increased risk
of dying from cancer,
and increased risk of dying
from all causes put together.
This all disappeared after
adjustment for confounding factors.
In other words, it wasn’t
the potatoes at all.
Potato eaters must just
smoke or drink more,
or eat more saturated
fat, or something.
Once you control for
all these other factors,
the link between potatoes
and death disappears.
This was confirmed in
the NIH-AARP study,
the largest such study of diet
and health in human history.
If you just separate out the
potatoes, researchers find
that they are not associated
with increased risk of death,
with the possible exception
of French fries, which are
associated with an increased
risk of dying from cancer.
Put all the studies
together—20 in all—
and no significant association
has been found
between potato consumption
and mortality, though again
fried potatoes
may be the exception.
Even just twice a week, fries
may double one’s risk of
dying prematurely, independently
of other factors;
but the consumption of unfried
potatoes seemed to be neutral.
You know, it’s funny. I’ve
done a bunch of videos on how
all plant foods are not
created equal, talking about
healthy vs. unhealthy
plant-based diets.
To this end, researchers created
not just an overall
plant-based diet index—just
scoring plant vs. animal foods—
but also a healthy plant-
based diet index (hPDI)
and an unhealthy plant-
based diet index (uPDI).
The healthy index puts a greater
emphasis on whole plant foods,
whereas the unhealthy index
scores how much low-quality
plant foods you’re eating,
grouping potatoes
along with soda, and cake,
and Wonder Bread.
Then, when you run the numbers,
the more plant-based you eat
the longer you live, the lower
your risk of cardiovascular disease.
In other words, more plant foods
and less animal foods are
associated with a significantly
lower risk of dying prematurely.
This benefit was limited,
though, to those eating the
healthier plant food diets,
but they were surprised that
those eating all that
processed plant-based crap
didn’t live significantly
shorter lives.
Now maybe, that’s just because
they were eating fewer
animal products, and that’s
really the primary determinant
of lifespan here, or maybe the
lack of an association between
less healthy plant-based diets
and mortality outcomes
is because potatoes were kind
of coming to the rescue.
And indeed, higher intake of
potatoes did appear protective;
so, given these conﬂicting ﬁndings,
future studies may consider
just resigning fried potatoes
to the unhealthy list.
Now, in terms of mortality, fried
potatoes may not be as bad
as fried meat—fried
chicken and fried fish—
but that’s not
really saying much.
The French fry death data
gave the industry trade group
Potatoes USA a bit of a
chip on their shoulder,
reminding readers that observational
studies can only prove
correlation, not causation,
to which the authors replied,
“our data add to the pressing
public health calls
to limit fried
potato consumption.”
French fries may be so bad for
you that it wouldn’t be ethical
to do an interventional study and
randomize people to eat them.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite to each of these topics.
For a timely text on the
pathogens that cause pandemics,
order the e-book,
audiobook, or hard copy
of my last book,
“How to Survive a Pandemic”.
For recipes, check out
my second-to-last book,
my “How Not to Diet Cookbook”.
It’s beautifully designed
with more than 100 recipes
for delicious and
nutritious meals.
And all the proceeds
I receive from the sales
of all my books goes to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the website is free.
There’s no ads, no corporate sponsorship.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.